We ask a lot of questions
about our diet.
What’s the right way to
treat a chronic illness?
Fight off a virus,
lose weight?
The problem is, we get
a lot of different answers.
Well, I’m here to help.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
It sounds like science fiction.
Bacteria in a vial of dirt
taken from a mysterious island
create a compound
that prolongs life—
and not just in
the traditional medical sense.
Thanks to advances
in modern medicine,
we are living longer lives,
but we're doing so
by lengthening
the morbidity phase.
In other words,
we are living longer
but sicker lives.
Traditional medical approaches
tend to just increase
the number of old people
in bad health.
Ideally, though, we'd extend
lifespan by slowing aging.
That way we could delay
the onset of deterioration,
rather than just extend
the period of deterioration.
That's exactly what this
new compound appeared to do.
Researchers called it rapamycin,
named after the bacteria's home,
the mystical Easter Island famed
for its rock-carved figures,
which is known locally
as Rapa Nui.
Rapamycin inhibits an enzyme
that's come to be known as mTOR,
or "mechanistic target
of rapamycin," a key modulator
of aging, characterized
as a "master determinant
of lifespan and ageing."
What does the enzyme mTOR
actually do?
It is the major regulator
of growth in animals.
Activation of mTOR drives
increases in both cell size
and cell number.
What's wrong with that?
The action of mTOR
has been described as the engine
of a speeding car
without brakes.
In this analogy, aging is
a hurtling car that enters
the low-speed zone
of adulthood and damages itself
because it does not
and cannot slow down.
We are over the hill
and picking up speed.
Why don't living organisms
have brakes?
Because they've
never needed them.
In the wild, animals often
don't live long enough
to experience aging.
Most animals die before they
even reach adulthood.
The same used to be true
for humans.
Due to early age mortality,
in the 17th century
most Londoners
didn't even make it to age 16.
So, living beings need to grow
as fast as possible to start
reproduction before they die
from external causes.
The best evolutionary strategy
may therefore be
to run at full speed.
However, once we pass
the finish line, once we win
the race to pass on our genes,
we're still careening forward
at an unsustainable pace,
all thanks to this enzyme mTOR.
In our childhood,
mTOR is an engine of growth,
but in adulthood,
it can be thought of
as the engine of aging.
Nature simply selects
for the brightest flame,
which in turn casts
the darkest shadow.
This is the so-called
trade-off theory of aging,
a concept technically known
as antagonistic pleiotropy,
in which a gene can have
a positive effect when young,
but a negative effect when old.
This explains how genes with
deleterious effects late in life
can persist in a population.
For example,
the pro-inflammatory
"Alzheimer's gene"
appears to protect
against childhood infections,
a major killer
throughout most
of human existence.
What's the downside
of unconstrained growth
fueled by mTOR?
The enzyme plows
full steam ahead,
revving up construction pathways
to churn out
cellular building blocks
for new growth,
which can include
cancerous tumors,
while canceling
any renovation or demolition.
To preserve growth at all costs,
mTOR actively suppresses
autophagy,
countermanding
cellular cleansing
and rejuvenation.
In my autophagy chapter
in How Not to Age
I explain how this can lead
to accelerated aging.
Conversely, slowing things down
by putting the brakes on mTOR
appears to decelerate
the aging process,
extending life and health.
Inhibiting mTOR is considered
the best-validated
aging regulator.
In our next story,
we look at how Rapamycin appears
to be a universal anti-aging drug,
extending the lifespan of
all animals tested to date.
The soil bacteria
on Easter Island
weren't making rapamycin
to slow down aging,
but rather
to slow down the growth
of its natural enemy,
soil fungi (just like fungi
make penicillin to wipe
out competing bacteria).
Fungi from yeast on up,
like all plants and animals,
have mTOR genes.
This target
of the rapamycin enzyme is
the universal growth regulator
of advanced lifeforms.
So, while rapamycin
originally drew attention
as an antifungal drug,
we soon learned
it had many other effects.
Dozens of published studies
have demonstrated
that rapamycin,
by slowing down mTOR,
extends both the average
and maximum lifespans
of laboratory mice.
In fact,
rapamycin appears to be
a universal anti-aging drug,
extending the lifespan
of all animals and organisms
tested to date—
the only known drug to do so.
It can even work
when started in mid-life.
The original National Institute
on Aging Interventions
Testing Program experiment
in 2009 was delayed
because the researchers
were having difficulty
keeping rapamycin stable
in the mouse food
pelleting process.
(It can't just be dissolved
in their drinking water
because it's fat soluble.)
By the time
they were up and running,
the allotted batch of mice
were 600 days old,
which is equivalent to, like,
60 years of age in humans.
Even though the mice started
the drug so late in life,
their lifespans
were still extended
by about 12 percent,
which could equate
to more than an added
seven years of human life.
Initially, it was debated
whether rapamycin
was a true
anti-aging intervention
or "merely"
a potent anticancer agent,
lengthening lifespans
by just preventing
cancer formation.
mTOR signaling is hyperactive
in up to 80 percent
of human cancers,
where it plays a pivotal role
in sustaining tumor growth.
Rapamycin is used clinically
to prevent the rejection
of organ transplants
(by suppressing
the proliferation
of immune cells
that attack the new organ),
and a peculiar side effect
was found.
In a set of 15 patients
who had biopsy-proven
Kaposi's sarcoma
(a cancer
that often affects the skin),
all sarcoma skin lesions
disappeared
in all patients
within three months
after starting
rapamycin therapy.
The cancer just vanished.
As TOR is the master regulator
of cellular growth,
the cancer remission was not
completely unsurprising,
but subsequent
rapamycin studies showed
it can do so much more.
In animal models, rapamycin
extends healthspan too.
Rapamycin can ameliorate
age-related declines
in cognitive function
and physical function,
prevent hearing loss,
artery dysfunction
and tendon stiffening,
regenerate the periodontal bone
that holds teeth in place,
and even rejuvenate
the hearts of aged mice.
Remarkably,
health and longevity benefits
could be achieved
with intermittent
or transient dosing,
like getting one dose
every five days
or for just a few months
during middle age.
As a dog dad,
I was excited to read
about the Dog Aging Project,
where people brought
their middle-aged
companion canines
to be randomized
to low-dose rapamycin
or placebo for 10 weeks.
Like in the mouse studies,
rapamycin appeared
to at least partially reverse
some of the age-related
heart dysfunction
without any untoward
side effects.
Anecdotally, most of the owners
of the dogs
who covertly got the rapamycin
reported their dogs displayed
increased activity and energy
compared to only a minority
of the owners of the pooches
slipped the placebos.
It was time to try
rapamycin out in humans,
which I'll cover next.
In Alzheimer's brains
on autopsy,
markers of mTOR activation
have been found to be
as much as 100 times higher
than age-matched brains
of those dying
from other causes.
That makes sense,
since nerve cells rarely divide
once they reach maturity,
which would otherwise dilute
damaged cell debris,
autophagy is particularly
important in the brain.
Given the "striking" improvement
in cognitive function
in old mice
from the mTOR blocker rapamycin
and studies showing
the prevention
(and possible restoration
in some cases)
of memory defects
in transgenic mouse models
of Alzheimer's disease,
there have been calls
for clinical trials
of rapamycin
for Alzheimer's patients.
After all, mTOR regulates
Alzheimer's biggest risk factor,
aging itself.
The risk of developing
this dementia
approximately doubles
every five years
over the age of 65,
with the risk of death
from Alzheimer's skyrocketing
approximately 700-fold
from age 55 to 85.
Unfortunately,
no such clinical trial
has been attempted.
It doesn't even look
like the dementia rates
of organ transplant patients
given rapamycin
have ever been tracked.
When kidney transplant patients
are initially switched
to mTOR inhibitors,
they do seem to experience
a significant improvement
in executive function,
memory, and mood,
but that may be in part
because they were switching
from drugs like cyclosporine
which can on their own cause
adverse
neuropsychiatric effects.
Rapamycin has been off-patent
for more than a decade;
so, drug companies
can no longer charge
whatever they want.
Without such price protection,
there isn't
a strong profit motive
to study the drug,
so we shouldn't expect
any large clinical trials
anytime soon.
Another reason
for clinical trial hesitancy
may be the frequent,
and sometimes life-threatening,
side effects,
like immunosuppression.
In one cancer trial
of an mTOR inhibitor,
for example,
two of the eighteen patients
developed
life-threatening infections,
and one of them died.
To fight cancer
or organ rejection,
we may be willing
to put up with significant risk.
But there's
a much lower risk tolerance
for anti-aging drugs
meant to be used en masse
for healthy humans.
The mouse longevity trials
are impressive,
but they're typically performed
in a strictly controlled
pathogen-free environment
that may not translate out
into real-world conditions.
The immunosuppressive
effects alone
are considered sufficient
to caution against
self-experimentation.
Nevertheless, there is a clinic
devoted to patients
who self-medicate
with rapamycin
in an attempt to slow aging.
Rapamycin advocates point out
that the doses required
for anti-aging are much lower
than used in cancer therapy
or organ transplantation
and, if anything,
might rejuvenate immunity.
Is it possible that transient
and/or intermittent dosing
could also help
reap the benefits
without as many risks?
You don't know
until you put it to the test.
Two small pilot studies
of low-dose rapamycin
for a few months
in the elderly
didn't cause
any major side effects
(though did cause diarrhea
in up to 62 percent),
but also failed to find
any immediate benefits
to cognitive function
or physical performance.
In 2018, however,
hundreds of individuals
age 65 and older
were randomized
to mTOR inhibition
about 100-fold lower
than what's used in oncology
or transplant patients.
And instead of
immune suppression,
they did appear
to get immune rejuvenation.
Not only did they experience
an improvement
in their response
to flu vaccination,
but they experienced
significantly lower infections
in the subsequent year
compared to placebo,
and they only got the drugs
for six weeks.
This suggests
a persistent improvement
in immune function
months after
discontinuing the drug.
Still, self-experimentation
continues to be
strongly discouraged
until we have a better idea
of the risks.
Thankfully, there are ways
to suppress mTOR
without taking drugs.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you hear about any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest major book,
“How Not to Age” is out.
Check it out from your
local public library.
I also wrote a
mini book on Ozempic.
Available in softcover,
e-book, and audio versions.
Check it out on NutritionFacts.org.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There are no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.